Finding Aid for William Harold Payne papers, 1853-1933
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Harold Payne papers 1853-1933
Payne, William Harold, 1836-1907.
2 linear feet
852065 Aa 2
Professor of pedagogy at the University of Michigan; chancellor of University of Nashville and president of Peabody Normal College. Correspondence and other papers concerning his activities in education and family matters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Frank R. Payne (donor no. 262 ) and came to the library in 1937.
The collection is open to research.
William Harold Payne was born May 12, 1836 in Ontario County, New York. He was educated at the Macedon Academy while also teaching in country schools. Around 1858, he became principal of a school in Three Rivers, Michigan. In 1864, he became principal of the union school at Niles, Michigan. From 1866 to 1869, he served as head of Ypsilanti Seminary, then left to become superintendent of public schools at Adrian. In 1879, he came to the University of Michigan as a professor of pedagogy. In 1887, Payne accepted the dual position of chancellor of the University of Nashville and president of Peabody Normal College in Nashville. In 1901, he returned to the University of Michigan. He died June 18, 1907.
The collection has been arranged into two series: Correspondence and Other papers. The correspondence dates from 1853 to 1933 and includes many letters addressed to his second wife Elizabeth Clark prior to their marriage. The Other Papers series concerns his activities as an educator and college president. Materials in this series include addresses, lectures, autobiographical and biographical volumes, personal account books, visual material, and other miscellaneous notebooks.
Subjects:
Education--United States.; George Peabody College for Teachers.; Teachers--United States.; Universities and colleges--Michigan.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Nashville.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Ann Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Carts and wagons.; Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; North Carolina.; Payne, William Harold, 1836-1907.; University of Nashville.
Contributors - Visual Materials:
Freer, Frederick W.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Douglas, Lloyd C. (Lloyd Cassel), 1877-1951.; Hinsdale, B. A. (Burke Aaron), 1837-1900.; Payne, Elizabeth Clark.
Genre Terms:
Account books.; Drawings.; Photographs.; Prints.
- Correspondence
  - 1853-1878 (Box 1)
  - 1882-1883 (Box 1)
  - 1884 (Box 1)
  - 1885-1886 (Box 1)
  - 1887-1889 (Box 1)
  - 1890 (Box 1)
  - 1891-1892 (Box 1)
  - 1893 (Box 1)
  - 1894 (Box 1)
  - 1895 (Box 1)
  - 1896 (Box 1)
  - 1897 (Box 1)
  - 1898 (Box 1)
  - 1899 (Box 1)
  - 1900 (Box 1)
  - 1901-1902 (Box 1)
  - 1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904-1906 (Box 1)
  - 1907 (Box 1)
  - 1908-1909 (Box 1)
  - 1913-1922 (Box 1)
  - 1923-1933 (Box 1)
  - Undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous telegrams (Box 1)
- Other papers
  - Autobiography (Box 2)
  - Genealogical and biographical information (Box 2)
  - Payne's library (contents of library with some prices) (Box 2)
  - Speeches given at Peabody Normal College, 1890-1894 (Box 2)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 2)
  - Lectures dictated to his wife by W.H. Payne (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 2)
  - Lecture notes (Box 2)
  - Contracts and receipts (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning Peabody Normal College (Box 2)
  - Papers concerning the expulsion of Howard W. Chaffin from the University of Nashville, 1898 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and other printed material (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Visual Materials (Box 2)
    Portraits, including etching by Frederick W. Freer; photographs of the Payne home on Ann St. in Ann Arbor, Michigan, and of the Chancellor's House, University of Nashville; photos of North Carolina, ca. 1890; sketch of University of Michigan professor, Isaac Newton Demmon; and miscellaneous.
  - Volumes containing miscellaneous writings, lectures, and notes (Box 2)